Inventory of the Edward D. Crippa Papers, 1948-1956
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Edward D. Crippa papers
1948-1956
Crippa, Edward D. (Edward David), 1899-1960.
05848
2.05 cubic ft. (5 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
The papers of Edward D. Crippa, who was appointed to represent Wyoming in the United States Senate in 1954, consist of correspondence, case files, and subject files.
Biography of Edward D. Crippa
Edward David Crippa (1899-1960) of Rock Springs, Wyoming, was appointed to the United States Senate in June, 1954, to fill the vacancy created by the death of Lester Calloway Hunt. He served only six months in the Senate. Crippa was a businessman in Rock Springs, served as Wyoming State Highway Commissioner from 1941-1947, was a delegate to the Republican National Convention in 1944, and was on the Republican National Committee from 1948-1960.
Scope and Content
The collection includes correspondence regarding constituent concerns, political appointments, and pending legislation. Subject files include the Laramie (Wyoming) Alumina Plant; Arizona Creek Toll Station near Jackson, Wyoming; the 1954 drought in Wyoming and the West; grazing legislation; and the U. S. Senate censure proceedings against Senator Joseph McCarthy. There are files on four reclamation projects (Echo Park Dam, Glendo Dam, the Missouri River, and the Upper Colorado River). Also included are legislative files and a 1956 speech kit from the Republican National Committee.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
As of the date of processing, there are no known other archival collections created by Edward D. Crippa.
Acquisition Information
The material was received from an unknown donor prior to 1975.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of select material from this collection are available at https://digitalcollections.uwyo.edu/luna/servlet/uwydbuwy~191~191.
Access Terms
McCarthy, Joseph, 1908-1957.; Republican National Committee (U.S.); Republican Party (Wyo.); Missouri River Basin Project (U.S.); Colorado River Storage Project (U.S.); Grazing -- West (U.S.); Water resources development -- Wyoming.; Water resources development -- West (U.S.); Droughts -- West (U.S.); Drought relief -- West (U.S.); Toll roads -- Wyoming -- Teton County.; Aluminum oxide industry -- Wyoming -- Laramie.; Cold War; Communism; Wyoming -- Politics and government.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-1953.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1953-1961.; Echo Park Dam (Colo.); Wyoming -- History -- 1946-; Glendo Dam (Wyo.)
Politics, Government, and Law; Laws and Legislation; Politics and Politicians; Agriculture and Natural Resources; Wyoming
Container List
- Series I. Administrative
  - Bills and Receipts, 1954, undated (Box 1)
  - Letterhead Stationery, undated (Box 1)
    Blank sheets and envelopes.
  - Office Affairs, Stationery, and Equipment, 1954, undated (Box 1)
    Includes bills, receipts, and correspondence.
  - Political File (Appointments), 1954 (Box 1)
  - Waiting Lists, 1954, undated (Box 1)
    A list of constituents awaiting delivery of government publications. Also includes correspondence regarding delivery of government publications.
  - Yellowstone Post # 2316 (Mr. John S. Angelovich, quartermaster), 1954 (Box 1)
    Order form and correspondence regarding two artillery pieces that were to be placed on the World War II Memorial grounds in Rock Springs, WY.
- Series II. Case Files
  - Alumina Plant, 1954 (Box 1)
    Correspondence regarding disposal of the plant in Laramie.
  - Arizona Creek Toll Station, Jackson, Wyoming, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Dr. J.T. Breihan (Miss Mie Takahata—Immigration), 1954, undated (Box 1)
    Incoming and outgoing correspondence regarding the immigration of a Japanese nurse.
  - Jennings Bryan Davis, Jr. A2C (Mr. Teno Roncalio, attorney), 1954 (Box 1)
    Correspondence regarding an investigation of Davis, a member of the Air Force who refused to provide financial support for his family.
  - Drought – 1954, 1954, undated (Box 1)
    Includes correspondence and clippings.
  - Matthew R. Frampton – Re: FHA Loan, 1954 (Box 1)
    Correspondence regarding a constituent’s difficulty in getting a Federal Housing Administration loan.
  - Rock Springs P.O. Lighting, 1954 (Box 1)
    Correspondence regarding the need for light fixtures at a post office in Rock Springs, WY.
  - John T. and/or David Williams – Re: O.C.S. Training, 1954 (Box 1)
    Correspondence regarding a constituent’s interest in enrolling in Officer Candidate School.
- Series III. Correspondence
  - Incoming
    - 1955, undated (Box 1)
  - Incoming and Outgoing
    - 1952-1954 (Box 1)
    - 1954 (Box 2)
    - Senator Frank A. Barrett (R-WY), 1954 (Box 2)
    - Invitations, 1954, undated (Box 2)
      Includes copies of some of Crippa’s replies to invitations.
    - Telegrams, 1954-1956, undated (Box 2)
- Series IV. Legislation
  - Acreage Limitation – S. 3071 (160 acres), 1954 (Box 2)
    Correspondence and notes regarding proposed legislation.
  - Agricultural Act of 1954 (Box 2)
    Includes copies of the proposed legislation and correspondence.
  - Atomic Energy Legislation, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Civil Aeronautics Act (S. 3759 and H.R. 8898 - Hinshaw Bills), 1954 (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence regarding the bills.
  - Grazing Bill – S. 2548 (Hope-Aikem-Thye Bill), 1954 (Box 2)
    Includes copies of the proposed legislation and correspondence. Also includes materials related to the Agricultural Act of 1954.
  - Grazing Bill – S. 2548 (Hope-Aikem-Thye Bill), 1954 (Box 3)
  - Legislative Recommendations – 83rd Congress, 1954 (Box 3)
  - Voting Record, 1954 (Box 3)
    A record of Crippa’s votes in the Senate. According to the record, his first vote took place on 6/29/54. The record of votes runs through 8/20/1954.
  - Assorted, 1954 (Box 3)
    Includes incoming and outgoing correspondence regarding various bills.
- Series V. Press and Media Activity
  - Press Releases, 1954 (Box 3)
    Press releases from Crippa’s office. Also includes a press release from the Eisenhower administration regarding the Disaster Relief Act.
- Series VI. Subject Files
  - Agriculture, 1954, undated (Box 3)
  - Bureau of Land Management, 1954 (Box 3)
  - Civil Service Examinations, 1954 (Box 3)
  - Department of Interior, 1954 (Box 3)
  - Drought Aid, 1954 (Box 3)
  - Echo Park Dam (Reclamation), 1953-1954, undated (Box 3)
  - Farmers Home Administration, 1954 (Box 3)
  - G.I. Housing Loans, 1954 (Box 3)
  - Glendo Dam (Reclamation), 1954, undated (Box 3)
  - Interior & Insular Affairs Committee, 1953-1954 (Box 3)
  - Kendrick Project, 1954 (Box 3)
    Correspondence regarding the sale of water belonging to the Kendrick Project in Wyoming.
  - Laramie Alumina Plant, 1954, undated (Box 3)
  - Joseph McCarthy, 1954 (Box 3)
    Letters in support of McCarthy and against his censure (several mention Major Irving Peress, who was investigated during the Army-McCarthy hearings). Also includes clippings.
  - Military Affairs – Army/Navy, 1954 (Box 4)
    Includes correspondence and government publications.
  - Missouri River (Reclamation), 1954, undated (Box 4)
    Resolution and correspondence regarding the Missouri River States Committee (made up of governors and representatives from the ten Missouri Basin states) to negotiate a compact.
  - Joseph O’Mahoney, 1954, undated (Box 4)
    Correspondence regarding O’Mahoney, who, in 1954, ran for the Senate seat held by Crippa. One letter mentions O’Mahoney’s participation in the defense of Owen Lattimore, who was prosecuted in federal court for perjury before the Senate McCarran Committee’s investigation into Communism in the United States. Also includes a list of O’Mahoney’s record of supporting tax raises.
  - Post Office - 3¢ Air Mail Experiments, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Postmastership and Post Offices for Wyoming, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Republican National Committee 1949, 1948-1952, undated (Box 4)
    Includes lists of officers, executive committee, and members of the Republican National Committee for 1948, 1949, and 1951, the 1952 Republican platform.
  - Republican National Committee 1952, 1952-1955, undated (Box 4)
    Includes a telephone directory, lists of executive officers and members, correspondence regarding the 1952 Republican National Convention (held in Chicago), and a list of delegates to the convention.
  - Republican State Committee 1952, 1952, undated (Box 4)
  - Adrian Reynolds - Vernal Manila Highway, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Rock Springs Coal Extraction Plant (Low Temperature Carbonization – Knapp & Tufty), 1954 (Box 4)
  - Rural Electrification Administration, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Service Academies – Army, Navy, Air Force, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Small Business Administration, 1954, undated (Box 4)
  - Speech Information, 1954, undated (Box 4)
    Includes a publication titled “Communism – Republicans! Wake Up! Don’t Let the Democrats Get Away with This One!”
  - Teton Park, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Upper Colorado River (Reclamation), 1953-1954, undated (Box 4)
  - Uranium Processing Plant Location: Wyoming, 1954, undated (Box 5)
  - Wyoming Game and Fish Commission, 1954 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming Natural Resources Board, 1952-1954 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming Stock Growers Association, 1954, undated (Box 5)
- Series VII. General
  - 1956 Speech Kit, Republican Congressional Committee, undated (Box 5)
    Spiral-bound notebook.
  - Assorted, 1954-1955, undated (Box 5)
    Includes a document regarding a dispute before the Civil Aeronautics Board, a petition advocating an appointment for William H. Harrison, reports from the Intermountain Soil Conservation District and the Bridger Valley Conservation District, a copy of a letter from Senator Francis Case (R-SD) to Arthur Watkins (R-UT) regarding censure charges against Senator Joe McCarthy (the letter mentions Major General Ralph Wise Zwicker—Major Irving Peress was one of his subordinate officers), and a resolution from the Department of Wyoming Reserve Officers’ Association that may be addressing the Joe McCarthy’s accusations against the U.S. Army (the language of the resolution is vague).